{"tossups": [{"question": "Joseph Warren was killed at this battle as one side retreated across Charlestown Neck after running out of gunpowder, leaving their opponents with a Pyrrhic victory. During this battle, Israel Putnam allegedly ordered his troops not to fire until they saw the whites of their enemies\u2019 eyes as British troops stormed a redoubt on Breed\u2019s Hill. For ten points, name this Boston-area battle that followed Lexington and Concord.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Bunker Hill</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The Tamworth Manifesto outlined the ideals of this modern political party. One prime minister from this party was a rival of William Gladstone and made Queen Victoria the \u201cEmpress of India.\u201d Another prime minister from this party repealed the Corn Laws. This political party\u2019s leaders included Benjamin Disraeli and founder Robert Peel. For ten points, name this British political party, sometimes called the Tories, that traditionally stands opposed to the Liberals and Labour.", "answer": "<b> Conservative</b> Party", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The \u201cPolyphase Phase\u201d system was marketed under this man\u2019s name, while the SI unit for magnetic flux density was named in his honor, 17 years after his 1943 death. George Westinghouse bought patents to this man\u2019s induction motor, which prefaced Westinghouse\u2019s company partaking in the \u201cWar of Currents\u201d against the direct-current based Edison Electric Light Company. For ten points, name this Serbian-American who pioneered the use of alternating current systems.", "answer": "Nikola<b> Tesla</b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "Justice Scalia wrote that this practice was becoming \u201ca game\u201d after a ruling exempting the mentally disabled from it. The Court ruled that judges alone could not decide on this practice in<em> Ring v. Arizona</em>, and minors were exempted from it by<em> Roper v. Simmons</em>. Potential racial bias led the Supreme Court to declare laws on this practice too arbitrary in<em> Furman v. Georgia</em>, which was later overturned. For ten points, name this practice of executing those convicted of serious crimes.", "answer": "<b> Capital Punishment</b> (accept<b> Death Penalty</b> or equivalents)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Dwight Evans spent all but one year of his career with this team, which fielded three generations of Hall of Fame left fielders in Jim Rice, Carl Yastrzemski, and \u201cThe Kid.\u201d Pedro Martinez moved to this team from the Montreal Expos and helped the team end its championship drought of 86 years, allegedly caused by the team\u2019s sale of Babe Ruth to a certain rival team based in New York. For ten points, name this Major League baseball team that plays its home games in Fenway Park.", "answer": "Boston<b> Red Sox</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "These people produced the Kunz Axe, a notably large ritual artifact made of jade that was consistent with the \u201cwere [WAIR]-jaguar motif\u201d common in the art of these people. These people, the first to play the \u201cball game,\u201d were also known as the \u201crubber people\u201d for their ability to extract latex from trees. Their major sites included San Lorenzo and La Venta. For ten points, name this earliest known Meso-American civilization noted for producing giant stone heads.", "answer": "<b> Olmec</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man was forced to respond to the rebellion of Luis Mena by beginning a twenty year military intervention in Nicaragua. This man notably used a \u201cSaxbe fix\u201d to hire Philander Knox as his Secretary of State, appointing him to carry out \u201cDollar diplomacy.\u201d This Republican split votes with the Bull Moose party\u2019s Teddy Roosevelt in 1912, allowing Woodrow Wilson to become president. For ten points, name this man, the only person to serve both as president and Supreme Court justice.", "answer": "William Howard<b> Taft</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The fisherman Dictys took in this man and his mother after they were cast to sea in a wooden chest. This man received a magic wallet from Hermes and an invisibility helm from Hades. Grandfather to both Heracles and Helen of Troy, during one quest, this son of Danae stole a shared eye from the Gray Sisters. After killing a sea monster, this hero married Andromeda. For ten points, name this Greek hero who used a reflective shield during his slaying of Medusa.", "answer": "<b> Perseus</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "The first European to inhabit what would become this city was Portuguese merchant Juan Rodriguez. Peter Minuit legendarily purchased the land for this city from the Lenape [LEN-ah-peh] for 24 dollars worth of glass beads. Richard Nicholls captured this city from Director-General Peter Stuyvesant, and renamed this city from New Amsterdam to its present name. For ten points, name this city where traders founded a stock exchange under a buttonwood tree at Wall Street, which is on Manhattan Island.", "answer": "<b> New York</b> City (accept<b> New Amsterdam</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "With a name from the Greek for \u201cable to choose,\u201d one of these groups called the Lollards was created by John Wycliffe. A campaign led by Simon de Montfort targeted one of these groups in Toulouse, while another of these groups formed defensive squares with their wagons in battle. Examples of these groups include the Hussites, who were condemned at the Council of Constance, and the Cathars, who were attacked during the Albigensian Crusade. For ten points, name these historical groups that were persecuted for rejecting core Catholic beliefs.", "answer": "<b> Heretics</b> (accept word forms)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A 1958 film about this battle starring John Mills and Richard Attenborough was partly based on the novel<em> The Big Pick-Up</em>. Another film about this battle was shot using very little CGI and twenty \u201cLittle Ships\u201d which actually participated in this battle. That film about this battle, which was split into three sections named \u201cThe Sea,\u201d \u201cThe Air,\u201d and \u201cThe Mole,\u201d starred Harry Styles and is widely considered to be the best work of its director Christopher Nolan. For ten points, name this battle during which British and French forces were evacuated from France.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Dunkirk</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "This country failed to capture Tangier after its King Edward\u2019s brother encouraged him to attack the city from Ceuta. Rulers from this country\u2019s House of Aviz sponsored Bartolomeu Dias\u2019s expedition to the Cape of Good Hope and Vasco da Gama\u2019s voyage to India. Along with Spain, this country signed the Treaty of Tordesillas, dividing up much of the New World. For ten points, name this country, whose Age of Discovery began in Lisbon.", "answer": "<b> Portugal</b> (or<b> Portuguese</b> Empire)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In one novel written in this language, Marius joins the Friends of the ABC. In another novel originally written in this language, Athos, Porthos, and Aramis form the title group, who adopt the motto \u201cAll for one, one for all.\u201d<em> The Three Musketeers</em> was originally written in it, as was a novel where the gypsy Esmeralda is rescued by the deformed Quasimodo. For ten points, name this language which Victor Hugo used to pen<em> Les Miserables</em> [lay mee-zah-RAH-bluh] and<em> The Hunchback of Notre Dame</em>.", "answer": "<b> French</b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "One piece by this composer was based on a poem by Friedrich Schiller and was unusual for its length and its use of a choral section. After learning Napoleon crowned himself emperor, this man changed the nickname of his third symphony to<em> Eroica</em>. The first four notes of his fifth symphony inspired the \u201cV for Victory\u201d symbol used to show Allied support during World War Two. For ten points, name this deaf composer whose Ninth Symphony includes a setting of \u201cOde to Joy.\u201d", "answer": "Ludwig van (or von)<b> Beethoven</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One politician described this law as a \u201ctitle page to a great, tragic volume.\u201d John Taylor and Jesse Thomas introduced many parts of this law that was described as a (+) \u201cFire bell in the night\u201d by Thomas Jefferson. James Tallmadge attempted to add a proposal to this law that would have made children of slaves free after the age of 25. This law led to the (*) </b>formation of Maine as a free state and was declared unconstitutional in<em> Dred Scott v. Sanford</em>. For ten points, name this 1820 law that allowed slavery above the 36-30 line.", "answer": "<b> Missouri Compromise</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A leader of this nation declared martial law at least partially in response to a (+) strike orchestrated by a union founded in Lenin Shipyard. One president of this nation</b> <b>won the 1983 Nobel Peace Prize based on his work founding the (*)</b> Solidarity trade union in Gdansk. For ten points, name this country where president Lech Walesa was the first democratically elected leader to govern from Warsaw.", "answer": "<b> Poland</b> (or<b> Polish</b> People\u2019s Republic)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man boasted that defeating the British would be as easy as eating breakfast. This man refused to reinforce La Haye Sainte, and his cannons were nullified by the reverse slope defense. A fatal charge by (+) Marshal Ney against retreating Englishmen was ordered by this man. This man deployed his troops from Plancenoit in order to capture Hougoumont but was hampered by the late arrival of Gebhard von Blucher at this man\u2019s (*)</b> final defeat. For ten points, name this Frenchman who died 1200 miles off the west coast of Africa on the island of Saint Helena.", "answer": "<b> Napoleon</b> Bonaparte", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}